you're listening to the AI native Dev
brought to you by
[Applause]
[Music]
Tesla on today's episode we're going to
be very much talking about tdd and how
you can write tests manually and then
have code generated from those tests uh
joining me today at Bala n house how are
you doing Bala I'm totally fine how are
you Simon I'm doing very well thank you
really happy to have you join our
podcast now now Bala similar to me Java
developer um for for many years uh tell
us a little bit about about your role
and what you do for sync yeah very good
thank you I'm working at sync SN is a
company that's a consulty company we're
based in Amsterdam in the Netherlands we
have three areas in which we specialize
we have the data area this those are
people who work with Splunk cribble and
data engineers then we have the devops
people they work with kubernetes
terraform Cloud providers stuff like
that and lastly we have the development
unit and those specialize in Java
goodlin angular react stuff like that in
the past I started out as a Java
developer at syc about 10 years ago
actually in 10 days I will be exactly 10
years ago and I used a lot at a big Bank
in the Netherlands then I became a unit
manager of the development unit and and
two and a half years ago I became the
CTO of the company also noteworthy is
that I'm an international speaker since
2019 I like to stand on conferences to
tell people talk to people have
discussions afterwards I love it and it
also gives you a chance to be in podcast
because I assume you saw one of my talks
online absolutely yeah and actually one
of the sessions is similar to some of
the topics that we're going to be
talking about today was one that I saw
at devox and I think jbcn comp as well
was one that you one that you talked
about and it's a really interesting
topic when we think about when we think
about tdd and how that plays a part in
AI development going forward first of
all tdd is that something that you have
always done is that something that you
do today in in in your normal
development pre AI
assistance a very good question I try to
it's not something I started out with I
learned about tdd I would say about 15
years ago and I think it's pretty hard
to do it uh the official way I think I'm
doing a little bit in the middle I read
a little bit of test and write a little
bit of code go back to the test so I'm
not a a die hard tdd but I like it a lot
it helps me to develop faster and
develop better yeah and and and from the
from the AI point of view looking at uh
the various AI assistant that that uh
that are in use today are first of all
are there AI assistant tools that you
find particularly useful in your daily
workflows um and and secondly when you
think about how AI tools or AI powered
Dev tools can really help you in your
daily development with providing tests
where do you find the most value of a
tool uh is it the creating the test is
it identifying where to test where does
that lie for you yeah very good question
again I normally there's are several
things I use AI coding assistants I
prefer them to be my IDE because then I
know the context of the things I'm
talking about and I use them to just
generate code for me I use the if I just
press enter it does a proposal I like
that but I like even better that you can
chat with it and then you can reason
about the code and ask it to generate
something and to improve upon it I ask
it to generate test cases but that's
only when I already have an
implementation what we're going to talk
about is the other way around of course
and I also like it to find bucks
sometimes it really finds bucks and
sometimes it it comes up with really
interesting suggestions and oh while
reasoning about the code there were like
Corner cases I didn't think about so
yeah are various things I I use it for
it's providing you with things that you
you may be thinking too close the golden
path and it's trying to It's thinking
more without context as a result and as
a result focusing on areas that you
wouldn't necessarily pay as much
attention to perhaps and actually now
thinking about it if if you would
summarize it I use it like a virtual
pair program yeah ah interesting which
is really when we think about these
tools as AI assistants that's exactly
the kind of role that we want them to
play right and of course so you've Also
let's introduce something else that
you're working on now as a project as
well you building up on a on a project
that really really is trying to generate
code from the from the tdd style tests
that you have created earlier um tell us
a little bit about that approach first
of all yeah yeah let me also introduce
it a little bit how I came up on this
idea how where it came from last year I
had a talk I gave it several conferen
and meetups called the battle of the AI
coding assistant in that talk I compared
different AI coding assistants like get
up co-pilot jet brains AI system but
also jet GPT uh and I showed off the
features the things that I could do and
one of the features that I showed off is
the fact that they're capable of
generating test case based upon your
implementation so you give the
implementation ask for test cases and
they come up with test cases and it
works pretty well at the end of one of
those conferences a discussion started
that happens most of the times and then
somebody asked Can you also do the other
way around you as a human can you write
the test and then can you ask the AI to
come up with the implementation and I
said that's really interesting I don't
know but I'm going to investigate so I
started investigating this led to some
research and that to my new talk which
is tdd and gen perfect pairing in which
I investigate if it's possible to write
test as a human give it to the AI ask
for implementation and then use the same
test to see if the AI came up with a
proper implementation and that's the
thing yeah that I'm nowadays talking
about at conferences and also in this
podcast yeah it's interesting so we've
really generated both Styles you create
the code and then generate the tests and
then vice versa generating the tests and
having a I generate the generate the
code let's let's let's talk about the
first case first and then we'll then
we'll spend most of our time on the tdd
uh side on the first case when we're
when we think about tests are really
that kind of like last line of defense
we want to make sure our code is is
bulletproof or as bulletproof as we can
get it and we rely on those tests to
really validate our assertions that we
want on our projects or the code if AI
is generating that and saying yes this
passes or this fails what's the how do
we validate that actually the AI
generated test are actually being
generated correctly or covering the the
areas of our project that are the most
important is this a manual kind of
review on that output basically from the
AI or is there a better way of doing
that actually I'm doing a manual because
as we all know AI tends to come up with
things and sometimes they come up with
things that are untrue or incorrect uh
therefore you should always check the
output of of a large language model of
an AI so in the first case when you
write implementation and AI writes test
always check the test I noticed that it
sometimes comes up with cor coring cases
I didn't think about so that helps a lot
but in general it like I would say it
always comes up with a happy flow and
most cases also with edge cases and if
it doesn't you can just ask for more
tests and yeah it will help you it will
inspire you and like I said before it
see as a pair programmer that helps you
to achieve a higher level of software
yeah presumably you use you use the chat
functionality just in the same way but
against test code versus versus
development code as well and you can
talk about the coverage or talk about
what case it's trying to it's trying to
catch there as well and if we think
about it the other way around when
you're doing when you're basically doing
a TD because you're the one writing the
tests I guess you can ask AI to validate
some of your work there but
realistically those tests are
effectively validating the generated
code so it's less of a motion to then
manually need to go over the code
because you can make certain assumptions
based on the quality of your coverage or
the tests that you're writing is that
fair yeah so so I would say the other
way around a better way because if you
provide the test you provide a
specification because tests of course
are a specification of what you want but
you also provide a way to check the
output of an AI and that's something
that actually every area would benefit
from but not every area has something to
check the output of large language
models luckily we software developers we
have a way to check the correctness of
our implementation at unit test and
therefore the second way so from tests
to implementation is I would say A
Better Way yeah that makes a lot of
sense and I think you mentioned
specifications there which I think is
very interesting because obviously
specifications You' mentioned chat as
well which is more of a short-term
prompt whereas a specification you'd
think as you think as a longer document
which describes the project would you
say tests are enough to be able to
Define your specification or do you feel
like there are other things as well that
you need to add in to be able to Define
that project good question actually as a
homework I'll listen to a few of your
podcasts before right with James wart
and you also discuss a topic and and I
like what he said he said tests are not
enough but I think we should extend what
should be part of the test to make sure
that the AI has enough to come up with
an implementation and we have enough to
check the validity of this
implementation at the at this current
state how we are testing nowadays let's
say junit 5 test yeah probably there are
some areas there are missing areas let's
say security let's say performance but I
think we in the near future we should be
able to add that in the Testo as well
actually I already have ideas how you
can do if you add a per performance test
to your test suite and also run that
against the implementation of the AI you
already can cover the performance aspect
oh wow tell us a little bit more about
that one that sounds interesting yes so
I'm going to show off a a proof of ccept
tool that I created um I'm going to show
that in the next episode but now it just
Ed junit 5 test but okay you could
actually in junit 5 you could already
say you could already time and you could
say the assertion this um test should
run faster than 20 milliseconds and then
you already have some kind of
performance measurement so you could
work around that you could also say run
a pipeline and use security scanners to
see if there are no security BS in there
so everything is already there but it
just has to yeah become one package so
we're working towards I think a future
in which all those aspects can be fitted
into unit test or tests now you
mentioned that you watched the or listen
to the James ward Episode I'm G to ask a
similar question actually I'd love to
hear your opinion on this which is
really about projecting ourselves into
the future and thinking okay what what's
the whether it's source of Truth or the
most important artifacts when we think
about this idea of us writing tests or a
tdd style whereby the code gets
generated if the code is continually
being generated and the thing we're
changing are the tests what's going to
be more important in the future is it is
it going to be the tests or is it going
to be the generated code do you think
yeah I think the answer is simple if if
we trust the generated code from the AI
and that means if we trust or test yeah
then the test will obviously be more
important we don't care about the
implementation anymore actually
sometimes I'm playing with this tool
using the tool sometimes comes up with
implementation do are hard to read for
me that doesn't really matter because I
don't have to read the code anymore at
least in the future if we really can get
this yeah yeah going and I suppose you
could always ask AI to describe the code
for you I think we we're finding
ourselves in a far nicer place where AI
is like more understanding being able to
describe code in a far clearer way to
developers and I think that's that will
help the facts of the maintainability
through using AI as well so that's
really interesting and I think what I
know there's one other topic that we
should talk about which is really about
the purposes of test now I know you
mentioned Offline that there are two
purposes input and validation talk us
through you what you mean by that yeah I
think we talked already a lot about
using test as input so we as a human
right to test we give it to the ask AI
come up with an implementation that
pauses this test and that's where the
second purpose test come from we're
going to use the test to see if the
provided implementation is a correct
implementation and this is really where
the value of this method lies I said it
before sometimes AIS hallucinate come up
with things that are untrue but with
this test you can see if they came up
with a proper solution and I think this
is really
important way in this mechanism and and
what's the way what's the way that you
identify whether a proper solution is
has been gener
once I get the implementation from the
AI assistant I run the test canes and if
all tests are green if they all all pass
we have a perfect implementation and if
you trust your test actually you have
production ready code otherwise yeah so
that's the idea and uh it would also be
and let me share a story that really
highlights this problem of large
language models that they make of things
I think a half year ago there was a
story in the news about Air Canada which
is an air liner they have a website and
this website had a chatbot and they
decided to make this chatbot more
humanlike by using a large language
model which is by it in itself a good
idea so they implemented that and the
customer started talking with a jetbot
and they were talking about refund
policies so as you probably already
imagine where it is going the chatboard
started to make things up about this
refund policy so the customer was
foresighted and he made screenshots a
few weeks later he decided to make use
of his refund policy so he called the
helped us the actual humans behind it
and he said I would like to refund my
ticket and the people at the help they
said no that's not possible the jetboard
made mistake the customer disagreed he
said come on look at that screenshot I
want a refund he didn't get his refund
and he went to court and the judge
agreed with the customer the judge said
I don't care if it's a large language
model or a human that puts stuff on your
website if it's on your website it's
true therefore you have to honor the
agreement and Air Canada had to refund
the the ticket and the next day the
chatbot was offline I really think this
story highlights the problem we have
nowadays with chatbots uh you cannot
trust them for the full 100% they're
really useful but there's this last few
percents in which they yeah come up with
with false information yeah and and if
we relate that back to the tests then
and that's a really interesting story
and I think actually there's a lot more
to think about there just in terms of
the the verbal contracts really between
consumers and vendors but if we relate
that almost back to test and actually
think okay if if those errors or those
huc ations are actually appearing in our
code let's say okay the tests don't come
back green what what what's the next
step do we need to alter our tests do we
need to alter our code how do we know
which to which to change what in in this
project that you were creating what us
through that flow yeah let me let me
first do the happy scenarios and then we
will talk about when things go wrong so
in the happy part you as a human right
test you give it to the AI you ask for
an implementation this is the happy part
so we get a perfect implementation
production ready we run a test remember
happy path all tests are green so we
have implementation we can shift it to
production so this is Ideal World
unfortunately for us we don't live an
Ideal World so there are two lops Loops
in this mechanism first when we asked
the llm for an implementation it's
sometimes comes up with an explanation
that's not good enough we want an
implementation so we ask it again come
on this is we want an implementation
sometimes it comes up with a code that
doesn't compile that's also not good
enough we need compiling code otherwise
we cannot run the test this is the first
Loop then there's a second Loop
sometimes not all test passs if that's
the case we extract the errors from the
test and we feed them back to the large
language model and we say hey this field
come up with a better implementation
that will solve the problem that the
current version of the implementation
and so you get a feedback loop from the
test to the large language model and you
you feed the errors back to the large
language models and then you keep doing
that till you get a perfect solution of
course some things are unsolvable so
there are also max amount of rres in
there but normally it's capable of
solving problems and I'm going to show
you in the second part of this episode
or the next episode how we do that yeah
absolutely and and and in your
experience how many first of all
actually presumably you say which tests
are failing as well with the failures so
it can recognize which flows it needs to
concentrate on how many iterations do
you see it requiring typically before it
can go from a failing from let's say one
failing test to to all green yeah that's
a very good question but it really
depends like we always say yeah but the
more difficult problem the more Loops it
takes in the demo you will see some
things will be one shot Solutions also
interesting thing a large language
models are not deterministic so
sometimes they can fix a problem in one
shot and sometimes they not solve it
again then I rerun it and then it solves
it again in one problem the tool that I
created stops at five Rees so five Rees
for generating code and five Rees for
running the test and the majority of the
time it succeeds yeah yeah but that
depends really on the problems that you
feel the problem how complex in in the
demo after this we can simple and then
we're going to ramp up yeah so talk us
through a little bit before before we
close this episode for our listeners
this episode will be on obviously all
the podcast places as well as YouTube
second one you really need to kind of go
to YouTube to to watch this and we're
going to do a screen share and we're
going to show uh us creating tests and
then generating code based on those
tests and then effectively run that
against run the tests against the code
uh and see how many iterations Etc we
can get before we actually get a valid
uh work scenario tell us about those
scenarios that we're going to be doing
how complex are these problems that
we're going be trying to solve so we're
going to start a really simple we're
going to start manually the first test
that we're going to use is called the OD
even test every developer knows about OD
EV pretty simple problem you're going to
copy the code to Jet TPT we're going to
ask for an implementation copy this
impementation back to my ID and then
we're going to run the test this will
work of course then I'm going to make it
a little bit more difficult I'm going to
use prime number generation do exactly
the same thing then doing this stuff
manually becomes boring really fast so
we need something to automate this so
I'm going to introduce a tool which can
automate those tasks for you you provide
the tool with a test case and it just
talks to the large language model grabs
the feedback does the loops things I
talk about until all test passes and we
have a working implementation so the
first problem I had with this approach
is too much manual work that's why I
created the tool and then the second
problem I have with the tool is the fact
that the tool is pretty good at
generating plain Java code that's not
something what we do at our work place
right so we all use Frameworks and
libraries so I created a ma plugin that
can read your pom file it knows which
libraries which Frameworks you're using
and then I'm going to show off a simple
spring boot hello world and as last one
I'm going to show you the a more
difficult spring boot program that
there's an endpoint you give it a date a
birth date and it comes up with your age
amazing using real world scenarios with
a proper spring application not super
complex but certainly not trivial
applications for it so one more thing
about it really thing I started
developing this thing in the beginning
of the year and I do most of the things
at local large language models so
running on my laptop in the beginning of
the year it really troubles doing all of
those so halfway the presentation I had
to switch to Cloud large language models
but nowadays most of the exercises are
doable by the local llm have you
switched around with tried different
models and have you found big variations
between them are there some that are
maybe better at generating code or
understanding code versus others what
what did you land on yeah so uh uh let's
start with the local ones there there's
a lot of local bottles around there
played around with them but in the end L
three models are the best one for my use
case a few months back I switched to
llama 3 and nowadays I'm losing llama
3.1 and that works really well I think
it's one of the best local ones out
there and once I have to switch to the
cloud ones I used to use jet GPT which
works really fine nowadays I also use
CLA Sonet 3.5 and they also work really
well I haven't found a big difference in
those two yet but there are people out
there who say that the cloud one's
better
I yeah I've heard a mixture to be honest
I I always hear people raping about clae
models and a lot of the a lot of the
graphics I see show both Claude and 40
being very close together but they're
being then a gap between them too and
other models so yeah interesting to see
the differences there but yeah great to
hear your take that's the end of our
chat we're going to go into a deep dive
now for the next session for those who
want to track that as well and I very
much recommend you watch because I've
seen this before and it's amazing to see
this in action we're going to be writing
tests and generating code from those
tests so if you want to follow along
with that do check us out on the Tess
podcast page or the YouTube page direct
join us soon and thanks very much Bala
speak to you soon thank you Simon for
inviting me and see you soon byebye
[Music]
[Applause]
thanks for tuning in join us next time
on the AI native Dev brought to you by
Tesla
[Music]